here's a non-standard way to find the
sum of the first n odd positive integers
using areas the sum of the first n odd
positive integers 1 + 3 + 5 and so on up
to 2 N minus 1 can be represented by an
array of 1x one squares like this where
the first row has one square the second
row has three squares and so on all the
way down until the very last row which
has 2 N - one squares this array has a
height of size n and a base of size 2 N
minus one like this
to find the area of this array we can
cut it into pieces using this diagonal
line of slope - one2 starting at the
bottom right corner of the top
square we can use that line to break the
diagram up into a variety of rectangular
and triangular pieces as shown here
first on the left side we see a 1xn
rectangle the triangle in the middle is
2 N - 2 by nus1 and the nus1 triangles
on the right are all 2 2x1 triangles the
rectangle has an area of n * 1 or n the
large triangle has an area of 12 N - 1 *
2 N - 2 which is n -1 * n -1 or n^2 - 2
n + 1 and finally the N -1 triangles on
the right all have an area of 1/ 12 * 1
* 2 or 1 combining these areas together
we get that the sum of the first n odd
positive integers is n + n^ 2 - 2 n + 1
+ N - 1 but this simplifies to n^2 and
therefore the sum of the first n odd
positive integers is
n^2 to write this more compactly we have
that the sum where K ranges from 1 to n
of 2 K minus 1 must equal n^ 2 this is a
classic formula but we proved it using
areas of rectangles and
triangles